Guide to the Campbell-Mumford Papers 1719-1980 (Bulk 1793-1892) MS 98
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Campbell-Mumford Family Papers
1719-1980 (bulk 1793-1892)
MS 98
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
10.0 Linear feet (26 boxes)
Most of the material in the Campbell-Mumford Papers focuses on William W. Campbell, his son, Douglas Campbell 1st, or Benjamin M. Mumford. Key topics include Mumford's business as an insurance broker, William Campbell's work as a judge and historian, and Douglas Campbell 1st's work as an historian. Much material focuses discretely on the Campbell family or discretely on the Mumford family; only with the marriage of Harriet Bowers Mumford Paige and Douglas Campbell 1st in 1865 were the two families intimately linked.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) See guidelines in Reading room for details.
Biographical Note
Born in Ireland in 1690, James Campbell immigrated to Boston, Massachusetts, in 1728, moved briefly to Londonderry, New Hampshire, in 1735, and finally settled in Cherry Valley, New York, in 1741. Marrying Sarah Thompson (1694-ca. 1773), he remained in Cherry Valley until his 1770 death; their union produced Samuel Campbell, who was born in Londonderry, New Hampshire, in 1738. Samuel served in the French and Indian War and ultimately was commissioned a second lieutenant in 1772. Active in the Revolutionary War as a member of the Tryon County Committee of Safety, he was involved in the so-called "Cherry Valley Massacre" in 1778 (a bloody skirmish between colonists and Native American and British forces), was steadily promoted through the ranks, ultimately achieving the rank of Colonel, and served in the state legislature after the war until his death. Having married Jane Cannon in 1768, Samuel sired a son, James S. Campbell, in 1772; in turn, James married Sarah Elderkin of Windham, Connecticut, in 1800. Along with his mother, his sister, and his brothers, James was held captive by Native Americans as a result of the Cherry Valley Massacre of 1778; they were exchanged after two years of captivity. Commissioned Cornet of Horse in 1798, James S. Campbell served as Judge of the Court of Common Pleas for Otsego County, New York. He inherited his father's property in 1824 and lived there until his death in 1870.
The marriage of James S. Campbell and Sarah Elderkin produced William W. Campbell in 1806. William attended Union College, practiced law, and served in Congress. Moreover, he was Judge of the Superior Court in New York City (1843-1855), was Justice of the Supreme Court in New York City (1857-1865), and was Judge of the Court of Appeals (1865). Notwithstanding his legal commitments, he authored The Annals of Tryon County, Life of DeWitt Clinton, Life of Mrs. Grant, and a work on Robin Hood and Captain Kidd. He visited Scotland when Queen Victoria first visited Inveraray Castle in 1847, inherited his father's estate at Cherry Valley in 1870, and died in 1881. His 1865 marriage produced sons Cleaveland and Douglas Campbell 1st.
Douglas Campbell 1st was born in Cooperstown in 1840 and was graduated from Union College in 1860 and from Harvard Law School in 1865. Serving in the Civil War as Captain and Brevet Major in the 121st New York Volunteers, Douglas subsequently married Harriet Bowers Paige, daughter of Alonzo C. Paige and Harriet Bowers Mumford. An eminent lawyer and amateur historian, Campbell authored, most notably, The Puritan in Holland, England, and America. He inherited the estate at Cherry Valley in 1881 and died in 1893, leaving four children, William A. Campbell, Harriet Mumford Campbell Greene, Maria Starkweather Campbell Whitehead, and Douglas Campbell 2nd, and bequeathing the family estate to William and Douglas 2nd. Douglas 1st's older brother Cleaveland, meanwhile, served as Colonel of the 23rd U.S. Colored Troops during the Civil War and died of wounds from Petersburg in 1865. Similarly, Douglas 1st's younger brother, Lewis, served as Captain in the 152nd U.S. Volunteers and was a prisoner of war for two years; he, too, died of war-related wounds.
By contrast, the Mumford family came to the American colonies in the early seventeenth century under the aegis of Captain John Smith. Thomas Mumford's great-great-great-great-grandson, Benjamin Maverick Mumford (1772-1843), was an insurance broker working in New York who married Harriet Bowers (1782-1868) in 1802. Their daughter, Harriet Bowers Mumford, married Alonzo C. Paige; the couple had a daughter, Harriet Bowers Paige, who went on to marry Douglas Campbell 1st, thereby bringing the families together.
Scope and Content Note
The Campbell-Mumford Papers focuses on the Campbell family (especially William W. Campbell and his son, Douglas Campbell 1st) or the Mumford family (especially Benjamin M. Mumford). Relatively little material focuses on the merger and subsequent history of the families once they were joined by the marriage of Harriet Bowers Mumford Paige and Douglas Campbell 1st. Types of material include court minutes, correspondence, published works, speeches, clippings, and business materials. Series are arranged by individual or by type of material and chronologically or alphabetically by subject therein. Most relevant materials include slave bills of sale and receipts, materials on the creation of the New York Soldiers' Home (for Civil War veterans), materials about family members' roles in the Civil War, and materials on the "Cherry Valley Massacre" of 1778, including subsequent debates not only over what happened but also over how historians have portrayed the events and the participants.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged within the following five series:
Series I. Campbell Family
Series II. Mumford Family
Series III. Bowers, Myer, Paige Families
Series IV. Printed Materials
Series V. Non-Family Materials
Series VI. 1980 Supplement
Campbell, Douglas, 1839-1893; Campbell, Douglas, b. 1873; Campbell, William W., 1806-1881; Mumford, Harriet Bowers, 1782-1868; Paige, Alonzo C. (Alonzo Christopher), 1797-1868; Starkweather, Samuel, 1786-1853; Union College (Schenectady, N.Y.); Cherry Valley (N.Y.); Otsego County (N.Y.)
- Series I: Campbell Family
  Scope and Contents note
  This series pivots around the Campbell family and incorporates twelve subseries.
  - Subseries 1: Genealogical Materials
    Genealogical materials (arranged alphabetically by title) trace the Campbell family back to its ancestral roots in Scotland and forward to its prominence in the United States from the eighteenth through twentieth centuries. These materials also adumbrate the Campbell and Mumford families' connection to other prominent American families.
    - "The Campbells of Cherry Valley" and Related Materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "The Campbells of Cherry Valley", 1861 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Earle Family fragment, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Genealogie of the Family of Achinbreck" (typed copy of 1741 manuscript), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Genealogies of American Families, number 33", undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The House of Achinbreck", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "A Notable Family", 1878 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Paige Family Genealogy, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Paige/Mumford Family Genealogy, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Scotland of Antiquity-The Clan Campbell", undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Untitled Genealogical Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 2: Samuel Campbell Materials
    Subseries two focuses on Samuel Campbell (1738-1824) and includes receipts, legal documents such as indentures, and notes dated 1769 to 1802. It also includes slave receipts and bills of sale. The subseries is arranged chronologically.
    - Samuel Campbell Materials, 1769-1802 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 3: James Campbell Materials
    Materials of Samuel's son, James Campbell (1772-1870), comprise subseries three and cover the dates 1800 to 1863; they, too, are arranged chronologically.
    - James Campbell Materials, 1800-1863 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 4: Robert, Lewis, A.E. Campbell Materials
    Subseries four deals with the small amount of material of other Campbell family members, e.g. Robert, Lewis, and A.E. Campbell.
    - Robert, Lewis, A.E. Campbell Materials, 1818-1865 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 5: William W. Campbell Materials
    Subseries five focuses on William W. Campbell (1806-1881), is arranged by relevance, and is one of the largest troves of material in the Campbell-Mumford Papers, incorporating correspondence, writings, and court minutes.
    - Correspondence and Related Materials, 1831-1881, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Writings, 1866-1879, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Court records book, Delaware County, 1858 January (Box 2)
    - Court records book, Otsego County, 1858 February (Box 2)
    - Court records book, Otsego County, 1858 June (Box 2)
    - Court records book, Otsego County, 1858 October (Box 3)
    - Court records book, Otsego County, 1858 December (Box 3)
    - Court records book, Chemung County, 1859 February (Box 3)
    - Court records book, Delaware County, 1859 May (Box 3)
    - Court records book, Chenango County, 1859 September (Box 3)
    - Court records book, Tioga County, 1860 March (Box 3)
    - Court records book, Chenango County, 1860 September (Box 4)
    - Court records book, Madison County, 1860 September (Box 4)
    - Court records book, Wayne County, 1860 October (Box 4)
    - Court records book, Chemung County, 1861 February (Box 4)
    - Court records book, Tioga County, 1861 March (Box 4)
    - Court records book, Monroe County, 1861 April (Box 4)
    - Court records book, unspecified county, 1861 April (Box 5)
    - Court records book, Otsego County, 1861 July (Box 5)
    - Court records book, Otsego County, 1861 September (Box 5)
    - Court records book, Otsego County, 1861 December (Box 5)
    - Court records book, Chemung County, 1862 February (Box 5)
    - Court records book, Otsego County, 1862 June (Box 5)
    - Court records book, Otsego County, 1862 July - 1862 August (Box 5)
    - Court records book, Tioga County, 1862 October (Box 6)
    - Court records book, Tompkins County, 1863 January (Box 6)
    - Court records book, Broome County, 1863 February (Box 6)
    - Court records book, Delaware County, 1863 August (Box 6)
    - Court records book, Madison County, 1864 February (Box 6)
    - Court records book, Otsego County, 1864 February (Box 6)
    - Court records book, Broome County, 1864 September (Box 6)
    - Court records book, Tioga County, 1864 October (Box 6)
    - Court records book, Otsego County, 1864 December (Box 6)
  - Subseries 6: Douglas Campbell 1st Materials
    The sixth subseries covers the work of Douglas Campbell 1st (1840-1893), especially his work as historian, attorney, and creator of the Soldiers' Home. It, too, is arranged by relevance.
    - Correspondence and Related Materials, 1866-1891 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Writings and Related Materials, 1878-1893, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Research Materials and Notes, 1866-1879, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - "The Campbell Current Record Volume 2: The Puritan in Holland, England, and America - Press Notices", undated (Box 7)
    - "The Campbell Current Record Volume 4: Letters Received by Douglas Campbell in relation to his work The Puritan in Holland, England, and America", 1886-1893 (Box 8)
    - Soldiers' Home Materials: Advertising and Journalism Materials, 1877 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Soldiers' Home Materials: Clippings and Related Materials, 1877, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Soldiers' Home Materials: Correspondence, 1877-1879, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Soldiers' Home Materials: Meeting Materials, 1877 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Soldiers' Home Materials: Pamphlets, 1868-1877 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 7: Cleaveland Campbell Materials
    Subseries seven tackles Cleaveland Campbell (d. 1865 of war wounds) and his Civil War service as Colonel of the 23rd Colored Troops.
    - Correspondence and Related Materials, 1860-1866 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 8: Douglas Campbell 2nd Materials
    The eighth subseries shifts to Douglas Campbell 2nd (d. 1950), an attorney like his father, and includes correspondence regarding the historical legacy of the "Cherry Valley Massacre" and a scrapbook that focuses on his experience at Union College and at Harvard Law School.
    - Correspondence, 1926-1936 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1893-1911 (Box 9)
  - Subseries 9: Campbell/Starkweather Album
    Includes invitations and letters from eminent Americans such as John Quincy Adams, Andrew Jackson, Martin Van Buren, John Tyler, Henry Clay, James Buchanan, Daniel Webster, William Seward, and George Bancroft, as well as autographs of H.W. Longfellow and E.A. Poe. Most of the material focuses on Samuel Starkweather or William W. Campbell.
    - Album, 1832-1850 (Box 10)
  - Subseries 10: Campbell Family Scrapbook
    Includes miscellaneous newspaper and periodical clippings (1878-1892) concerning the Campbell family.
    - Scrapbook, 1878-1892 (Box 10A)
  - Subseries 11: Campbell Family Visual Materials
    Includes plates, photographs, and maps.
    - Plates, Photographs, and Maps, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 12: Campbell Family Bibles
    - Bible, 1811 (Box 11)
    - Bible of Sarah E. Campbell, 1811 (Box 12)
    - Bible of William W. Campbell, 1811 (Box 13)
- Series II: Mumford Family
  This series hinges on the business activities of Benjamin Maverick Mumford (1772-1843), insurance broker and ship-owner of New York City and Schenectady, N.Y. Ranging in date from 1793 to 1842, materials include Notes of Hand, Orders for Insurance, correspondence, and accounts, as well as materials clustered around the activities of specific ships or voyages or both. Some material does focus on Mumford's descendents and relatives, but by and large the focus remains on Mumford and his business endeavors.
  - Brig Nancy and Related Materials, 1793 July-1794 December (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Business Correspondence, 1794 October-1795 August (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Notes Issued and Related Business Materials, 1795 February-1796 July (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Schooner John Materials, 1794-1797 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Brig Endeavor Materials, 1795 October-1796 October (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Notes of Hand, 1796 January-1796 December (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Brig Electa Materials, 1796 January-1797 January (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Brig Electa Materials, 1797 August-1797 November (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Notes of Hand and Related Materials, 1797 January-1797 December (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Brig Electa to Jacquemel, 1797 March-1797 August (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Notes of Hand and Related Materials, 1798 January-1798 December (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Brig Betsey Materials, 1798 February-1798 October (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Ship Peggy to Liverpool Materials, 1798 April-1798 November (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Schooner John Materials, 1798 May-1799 May (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Notes of Hand and Related Materials, 1799 January-1799 December (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Brig Penelope Materials, 1799 May-1799 October (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Orders for Insurance, 1800 January-1800 August (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Orders for Insurance, 1800 September-1800 December (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Orders for Insurance, 1801 January-1801 April (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Orders for Insurance and Related Materials, 1801 May-1801 August (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Orders for Insurance and Related Materials, 1801 September-1801 December (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Orders for Insurance and Related Materials, 1802 January-1802 March (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Orders for Insurance and Related Materials, 1802 April-1802 September (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Orders for Insurance and Related Materials, 1802 October-1802 December (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Orders for Insurance and Related Materials, 1803 January-1803 March (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Orders for Insurance and Related Materials, 1803 April-1803 July (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Orders for Insurance and Related Materials, 1803 August-1803 December (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Orders for Insurance and Related Materials, 1804 January-1804 April (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Orders for Insurance, 1804 May-1804 August (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and Related Business Materials, 1804 September-1804 December (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Schooner Harriet Materials, 1805 December-1805 November (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Orders for Insurance and Related Materials, 1805 January-1805 April (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Schooner Grey Hound Materials, 1805 February-1805 November (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Schooner Mary Ann Materials, 1805 April-1806 April (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Schooner Orestes Materials, 1805 June-1806 January (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Business Materials, 1805 April-1805 August (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and Business Materials, 1805 September-1805 October (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and Related Materials, 1805 November-1805 December (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Orders for Insurance and Related Materials, 1806 January-1806 March (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and Business Materials, 1806 April-1806 May (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and Related Materials, 1806 July (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and Related Materials, 1806 August-1806 September (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and Related Materials, 1806 October (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and Related Materials, 1806 November-1806 December (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and Related Materials, 1807 January-1807 March (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and Related Materials, 1807 April (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and Related Materials, 1807 May-1807 June (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and Related Materials, 1807 July-1807 October (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Business and Property Materials, 1808-1818 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Business, and Financial Materials, 1824-1842 (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Series III: Bowers, Myer, and Paige Family Materials
  This series contains sundry items related to the Campbell and Mumford extended families-specifically the Meyers, Bowers, and Paige families. Materials include deeds, indentures, and correspondence dated between 1760 and 1857 and is arranged by earliest date of first document.
  - Deeds and Indentures, 1760-1799 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Henry Bowers and Helena Myer Materials, 1789-1799 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - John R. Myer Materials, 1789-1811 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Mary Bowers Materials, 1803-1827 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - J.M. Bowers Materials, 1806-1827 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Mary Bowers Estate Record, 1811 (Box 21)
  - Alonzo and Harriet Paige Materials, 1833-1857 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Extended Family Notes, Accounts, and Related Materials, undated (Box 21, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Printed Materials
  This series contains printed materials authored or retained by members of the Campbell family and includes various publications and clippings dated between 1830 and 1945.
  - Subseries 1: Publications
    Arranged chronologically.
    - "The Massacre at Cherry Valley", undated (Box 22)
    - "An Abstract of the Most Important Alterations, of General Interest, Introduced by the Revised Statutes...", 1830 (Box 22)
    - "Description of a View of the Great Temple of Karnak, and the Surrounding City of Thebes, Now Exhibiting at the Panorama, Broadway, Corner of Prince and Mercer Streets, New-York", 1839 (Box 22)
    - "The Centennial Celebration at Cherry Valley, Otsego Co. N.Y. July 4, 1840" (Box 22)
    - "The Death of the Righteous Desirable: A Sermon, Preached at the Funeral of Mrs. Clarissa Paige", 1846 (Box 22)
    - "Opinion of the Honorable Lewis H. Sanford, Vice-Chancellor of the First Circuit of the State of New York, in the Case of Nathaniel Bogardus and Others, vs. the Rector, Church-Wardens, and Vestrymen of Trinity Church, in the City of New York, and Others", 1847 (Box 22)
    - "The Clinton Monument", 1848 (Box 22)
    - "The Philosophy of Spiritual Intercourse; being an Explanation of Modern Mysteries", 1851 (Box 22)
    - "An Oration, Delivered by the Honorable William W. Campbell, Judge of the Supreme Court of New York, February 23, 1852, at Metropolitan Hall, New York City, on the Occasion of the Celebration of the Birth Day of George Washington, by Order of United Americans" (Box 22)
    - "Address and Poem Delivered Before the Associate Chapters of the Sigma Phi Fraternity, August 16, 1853" (Box 22)
    - "An Address to the Graduating Class of the Law School of the University of Albany", 1857 (Box 22)
    - "Arguments of the Counsel of Trinity Church, Before the Senate Committee", 1857 (Box 22)
    - "Communication from the Governor in Answer to a Resolution Relative to the Abduction or Enslavement of Citizens of this State", 1857 (Box 22)
    - "Calendar of the Supreme Court", 1858 (Box 22)
    - "Remarks of Mr. Johnson, from Delaware, on the Bill Entitled 'An Act for the Trial of Certain Offenses'", 1859 (Box 22)
    - "Supreme Court. Tompkins County. Calendar of the Circuit for September, 1859" (Box 22)
    - "Tompkins County Circuit Calendar, for 1861" (Box 22)
    - "Green-Back to his Country Friends", 1862 (Box 22)
    - "Supreme Court Calendar, General Term, March, 1862" (Box 22)
    - "Supreme Court, Schuyler County. April Circuit and Special Term, 1862" (Box 22)
    - Obituary, 1864 (Box 22)
    - "Speech of Honorable Charles P. Daly, on the Judiciary", 1867 (Box 22)
    - "Address of the Union Republican Central Committee of the City and County of New York to the Republican Electors of the City and State of New York", 1869 (Box 22)
    - "Breach of Privilege, the Matter of Honorable H. Ray", 1870 (Box 22)
    - "Celebration of the 111th Anniversary of Robert Burns' Natal Day", 1870 (Box 22)
    - "The Mineral Springs of the United States and Canada", 1871 (Box 22)
    - "Address Before the Central New York Pioneer Association, at its Fifth Annual Meeting, at Syracuse, September 17, 1873" (Box 22)
    - "An Historical Account of the Presbyterian Church, at Cherry Valley, N.Y.", 1876 (Box 22)
    - "Retrenchment and Reform in the Government of the City of the New York", 1877 (Box 22)
    - "Central New York in the Revolution", 1878 (Box 22)
    - "Closing Argument of Douglas Campbell, Esq. in Reply to Gov. John C. Brown, J.A. Davenport, Esq., and Major James Turner, before the Judiciary Committee of the House of Representatives, in Regard to the Title of the Texas and Pacific Railway Company to the Property of the Memphis, El Paso and Pacific Railroad Company", 1878 (Box 22)
    - "Speech of Horatio Seymour before the Canal Committee of the Legislature of New York, April 9, 1878" (Box 22)
    - "The Address of the Honorary Chancellor of Union University, Honorable John K. Porter, LL.D., Delivered at the Commencement of Union College, June 25, 1879" (Box 22)
    - "Historical Fallacies Regarding Colonial New York, An Address Delivered Before the Oneida Historical Society, Utica, N.Y. at its Second Annual Meeting, January 14, 1879" (Box 22)
    - "Shall New York Expend $20,000,000 for a New Aqueduct, when Liverpool Has Solved the Same Water Problem for $250,000? A Paper Read by Douglas Campbell, Esq., Before the Municipal Society, April 12, 1880" (Box 22)
    - "The Address of the Honorary Chancellor of Union University, Honorable John Welsh, LL.D., Delivered at the Commencement of Union College, June 24, 1880" (Box 22)
    - "Tenth Annual Report of the Alumni Association of the College of Pharmacy, of the City of New York, 1881" (Box 22)
    - "Tenure of Office under the New York Charter. Civil Service Reform in Practice. A Paper Read before the New York Municipal Society, February 7, 1881, by Douglas Campbell" (Box 22)